<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Stefano Zanella's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.dontwakethecat.net/blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.dontwakethecat.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-22T18:58:30+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.dontwakethecat.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Stefano Zanella]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I just wanted to say thanks...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.dontwakethecat.net/blog/2013/09/22/i-just-wanted-to-say-thanks/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-22T19:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.dontwakethecat.net/blog/2013/09/22/i-just-wanted-to-say-thanks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Disclamer</strong>: this post is about feelings, and it's written by me, so don't
expect things to make much sense from now on. It might also be long, and I apologise in
advance for that.</p>

<!-- More -->


<p>This post started as a way to thank everybody I met at eurucamp last month in
Berlin, as I felt that a tweet wasn't enough, but it turned out to be the most
difficult piece I've ever written.<br/>
It took me more than a month, and it's just now, here on a plane flying back from Hamburg
after an amazing first So Coded conf, that I'm trying to put some final words on it.</p>

<p>It turns out that these words took a long time to be written down because of
the impact that those ten days in Berlin have had on my life. This impact
still provokes me tears as soon as I start reflecting on it; having a deadline
like a plane landing seems like the only way for me to call it a day for this
post.</p>

<p>eurucamp hasn't just been another Ruby conference. It has been a thrilling,
exhausting, emotionally dense week built around the city and the people, a week
that transformed me.</p>

<p>I'm not exaggerating saying that eurucamp turned me into a better person. I'm not talking
about technical skills or general knowledge or curiosity satisfaction; I'm talking about maturity and
self-consciousness as a human being. The more I reflect on it and the more I
talk about it, the more I'm sure the change eurucamp operated on me is a
permanent one, and one that will have a radical impact on my future self.<br/>
I think this is pretty astonishing, given that it all started just as an opportunity
to fill the gap left by a cancelled vacation on the lake of Kontanz back at the
end of July. I was just looking to relax, and I couldn't be more wrong
expecting just that.</p>

<p>The biggest change happened in me is the balance between the things that
matters in my life. To me, this change is kinda unbelievable. I used to
believe I was a totally uninteresting person, that people couldn't enjoy
spending their time with me, that I had nothing interesting to say, and so on.
So, in the end this feeling drove me to a fairly solitary road, with
sparse and occasional relationships, always facing the fear of being/looking
inadequate to other human beings. This resulted in me caring more about other,
more material aspects of life and basing many decisions on that kind of focus.<br/>
A week in Berlin, deeply surrounded by the Ruby community,
completely faded that fog of irrational fear and totally revolutionized my
inner list of life priorities.</p>

<p>I recognize now that what I want from life is being as friendliest as possible
to other people and enjoying everything that I can have in return. It is my
firm belief now, that as soon as you give a smile to someone and do your best
to be as open, friendly and respectful as possible, whatever comes back in return -
being it an opinion, a suggestion, a story, a hug or whatever - is to be
treated like a little treasure, something to safely store in your mind and take
care for the rest of your life.</p>

<p>Another realization I had, also, is that even if you get nothing in return (which is,
by the way, a very rare occurrence), there's nothing to worry about. Maybe you
can use that as an opportunity to improve yourself, but if you're not lying to
yourself and you're sure you've done the best you could to communicate with
someone else, there's nothing to regret. <em>Just do your best effort</em>.</p>

<p>To me, this is a liberating realization, as it makes the fog of my social
fears fade away and puts back a smile on my face. And guess what? This in turn
becomes a positive loop, since as I already said it's quite hard to get actually
<em>nothing</em> in return from people. It's up to you to figure out what the outcome
of a human contact is; sometimes it's obvious, sometimes it may require time
and additional experiences for that to become clear. To an extent, also, it's up to you
to decide <em>what to keep</em> from a human relationship.</p>

<p>Of course, all of this is due to the people I met and spent time with there.
I would like to thank all of them (but I also know that I'm going to forget
someone, so please forgive me in advance and let me know so I can hide my shame
by updating the post :).<br/>
I cannot avoid to start by mentioning
the staff of organizers. Without their continuous efforts to make such an
amazing conference, there would have been no ground for this change to happen
in me. Also, I think we all must thank them for the "vision" they had about a
<em>different</em> conference, one in which the focus was on making space for people to
interconnect - something that seems usually to be taken for granted or expected
to spontaneously happen. Believe me, that's not so obvious, and the fact they reserved
time for people to (almost) self-organize (which also means that everybody
could choose <em>where</em> to do <em>what</em>), before and during the conference,
changed the perspective of the whole week.
So, many many thanks to Dajana, Alex, Florian, Matthias, Guillermo, Fanny, Lucas, Josè,
Mari - and a huge sorry to all who I'm forgetting or didn't know about, this
thank is for you too!</p>

<p>I also want to thank Ellen for the patience of listening to my rusty spoken English
while trying to improve my 3-years-old-toddler German.</p>

<p>Many thanks to Joanne for the conversation in the first place, but most
importantly for the most gratuitous and warmly-feeling hug I've received ever.</p>

<p>Another important "thank you" to Justine, Jano and Darío. As every
photographer knows, no matter if hobbist or experienced, what we seek as
photographers is a chance to take the photo that nobody has taken yet. You gave
me that opportunity, and that matters to me. A lot.</p>

<p>A huge (you cannot imagine how HUGE) thank to my friend (can I say so?)
Ernesto, who is like the brother everyone would like to have. Thanks for the
stories, the patience, the nice words, the friendliness, the open hands.</p>

<p>Another huge thank to George, who not only contributed to the list of
encouraging stories I've collected during the week, but also revealed itself to
be a very nice and pleasant person. The day we spent together walking around
Berlin was awesome, and I'm even more grateful for this given we just exchanged
a couple of tweets and mails without knowing each other in person. To me, this
has been a revealing experience on how powerful and beneficial ignoring your
fears can be.
The only regret I have is that I missed to say a proper goodbye; I count that
as a promise to meet soon around London ;-)</p>

<p>I also have to thank everyone who shared a personal story with me. In no
particular order, and probably with many omissions: Fanny, Carmen, Carmen and
his husband Enrique, Jano, José, Darìo, Sebastian, Irene and Josh.</p>

<p>And finally, my most important thank goes to Julia. She knows why.</p>

<p>PS: If anyone finds the piece of heart I left in Berlin, please don't touch it.
I'll come back to pick it up later, I promise.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
